Alex Kasimov

al4str.ftw@gmail.com

+7 (922) 472-07-05

@al4str

Saint Petersburg, Russia

Frontend Developer

Leading frontend developer with more than 5 years of professional experience in designing and developing websites, applications, complex systems, libraries and tools for solving business problems, improving user experience, optimizing team's development and working processes.

Key Skills

Web technologies: HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Node.js, browser APIs and extensions.

Frameworks and libraries: React, Vue, Svelte, Express.js, Nuxt.js, GraphQL Apollo, Vuex, Redux, BEM, SCSS, PostCSS, Apache Cordova, Webpack.

Tools: DevTools, Git, Docker, IDEs, Lighthouse, Nginx, Photoshop, Illustrator, Linux.

Development: adaptive mobile-first markup, crafting component libraries, profiling and debugging, performance auditing and optimization, iterative refactoring and tech. debt liquidation, caching, network and efficient content delivery, working with graphics, internationalization (*i18n*), server-side rendering (*ssr*), accessibility (*a11y*), designing architecture, bundling and transpiling, code splitting, frontops and *CI/CD*.

Transferable: leadership and coordination of the development team, interviewing, code review, consultation of colleagues from neighboring teams, problems defining and solving, planning and reporting.

Professional Experience

5 years 9 months

"the_covert", St. Petersburg, Russia, Lead frontend developer

Sep. 2018 — Currently

- Iteratively **eliminated technical debt** of legacy code (*CoffeeScript*, *jQuery*, *Bootstrap CSS*, obsolete *Laravel* templates) that accumulated over 5 years in a monolith app of highload multilingual digital media, thus **speeding up development** and **reducing TTM**, while still **delivering** new **features**.
- Convinced business owners to **make** a smooth transition to the **modern** *Nuxt.js* application by presenting a prototype with average *Lighthouse* **score** 40 ± 5 (against < 10 for the existing app). Further performance audit and optimization **raised the score** to 60+ without any work from the devops and backend teams.
- Built from scratch a custom mobile-friendly **CMS** solution to **easily construct articles** from lego-like blocks, which **reduced** the **cost** to maintain a huge publisher team.

"Building yard", Tyumen, Russia, Frontend developer

Mar. 2018 — Sep. 2018

- Assembled a *SPA* **application** for **managing** automatically and manually generated **complex filters** for product lists of a construction and youth clothing stores to significantly **reduce** the **time** content teams spent on **creating** those filters and reduce the **number of** human **errors** during that process.
- Developed a couple of small **mini-games** (awarding promo codes) to **increase** users **involvement**.

With only a clean bare-metal server rack, one python guru and 2.5 months of work delivered MVP application that combines data (collected and analyzed by machine learning algorithms) and maps of major US cities to display statistics over map areas with a wide range of parameters: from the well-being of the selected neighborhood to vacancies and salaries inside one building.

"Beton24", Simferopol, Ukraine, Lead frontend developer

Sep. 2016 — Oct. 2017

- **Designed** and developed **client layer** of what later became one of the largest information and analytical portal for selection of suppliers of building materials covering **1700**+ cities in Russia and the CIS countries.
- Custom **CRM** interface for organizing interaction with **leads**, managing **content**, e-mail and sms mailing **templates**.
- Crafted **components library** (vanilla untranspiled *JavaScript*) **still powers** the project's *UI*.

Job during (and after) university

Oct. 2013 — Aug. 2016

• Over years, **aced** writing **clean markups** and polished skills of delivering **interactive experience** in the process of creating over **20+ landing pages**, **sites**, **applications** of various complexity, deeply immersed in the industry of commercial development.

Education Sep. 2011 — June 2015

Tomsk State University of Control Systems and Radioelectronics, Tomsk, Russia

- Bachelor's degree in Modeling and System Analysis
- Candidate for Bachelor in Information System Security